Birge Company Records, 1887-1980
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Birge Company Records
1887 - 1980
Papers and records of the Birge Company, a Buffalo-based wallpaper company.
5 boxes + 44 oversize v. (10 linear ft.)
Birge Company
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
Martin H. Birge was born on July 20, 1806 in Middlebury, Vermont. He came to Buffalo by way of the Erie Canal on September 24, 1834, and saw the growing city of Buffalo as an opportune place in which to establish a business. On October 15, 1834, he opened a dry goods store at 234 Main St., stocking general merchandise and wallpaper.
By 1866 Birge had devoted his entire business to retail and wholesale paper-hangings, believing himself to be the first such proprietor in the city. The store had made several moves: in 1844 to 144 Main St., and in later years to 160 Main and 174 Main.
The firm’s name was changed to M.H. Birge & Sons in 1875 when Martin’s sons George K. and Henry M. joined after graduating from Cornell University. In 1878 the family began to manufacture its own wallpapers in a five-story factory on Perry and Indiana Streets. On December 17, 1880 fire destroyed the building and much of the stock, and claimed the lives of twelve people. Operations resumed in the former Prince melodeon factory on Seventh and Maryland Streets. Birge & Sons began to sell sets (coverings for walls and ceilings), and business grew increasingly in the direction of wholesale distribution. The Main Street store was closed its retail business in 1891.
Martin H. Birge retired in 1892 and passed the business to his sons. George K. designed a machine to make flocked wallpaper, thus eliminating a great deal of manual labor while maintaining a high standard of craftsmanship.
On August 23, 1900, M. H. Birge & Sons was incorporated. In its first ten years the capital stock increased in value from $150,000 to $500,000. In 1906 George K. Birge’s son Humphrey opened a European office and in 1910 he became a vice-president of the firm.
M.H. Birge & Sons was known for the quality of its wallpaper and for the artistry that characterized it. Local landscape artists were hired to paint and develop the original prints. The best known of these, Charles E. Burchfield, designed landscapes in the mid-1920s that depicted the wildlife and scenic beauty of Western New York. Birge became the first manufacturer to introduce do-it-yourself, wet strength wallpaper. The wallpaper, called “Quick,” included a built-in adhesive and a plastic, washable surface coating. In 1958 Birge developed “Fabrique,” a durable non-warping vinyl that was pre-trimmed with permanent embossed designs.
Birge & Sons produced a high quality but expensive product which could not compete with cheaper imitations. The company was purchased by reed Forest Products Company in 1969. Gradually the Birge operations were shut down; the company was forced to close in 1982 when a buyer could not be found.
Birge, Martin H., 1806-1900; Burchfield, Charles, 1893-1967; Contracts; ledgers (account books); M.H. Birge & Sons Company; Reed Forest Products; Wallpaper New York (State) Buffalo
Leases, patents, copyrights and contracts, ca. 1904-1940; and financial records, including tax statements, (1921-1936), bank notes (1933- 1935), sales books (1913-1919), ledgers (1910-1933), journals (1912-1944), and cash books (1911-1933).
- Historical files, ca. 1910-1980; I
  - Birge wallpaper, ca. 1910-1976 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Press releases, ca. 1955-1960 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Charles Burchfield, 1922 - 1980 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Wallpaper history (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Decorated leather wallpaper (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Birge leathers, 1919 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Sales talk and promotional copy, 1951 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Clippings, 1921 - 1980 (Box-folder 1.8)
- Leases, 1907 - 1939; II
  - London and Germany, 1907 - 1916 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Buffalo, Chicago, Los Angeles, and New York, 1935 - 1939 (Box-folder 1.10)
- Patents, 1904 - 1940; III
  - Wallpaper printing machinery, 1904 - 1940; Includes Burchfield patents. (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Wallpaper design, 1912 - 1928 (Box-folder 1.12)
- Other legal records, 1904 - 1940; IV
  - Copyrights, trademarks, and letters of incorporation, 1904 - 1940 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Traveling salesman contracts, 1919 - 1924; Alphabetical by surname
    - Becker, Calely (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Campbell (Box-folder 2.2)
    - Chase, Clancy, Coffey (Box-folder 2.3)
    - Dennett, Dirksen, Eckardt, Ervin (Box-folder 2.4)
    - Finnegan, Hartsock (Box-folder 2.5)
    - Hicks (Box-folder 2.6)
    - Himmel, Homer, Johnson (Box-folder 2.7)
    - Knobeloch, Lawrence (Box-folder 2.8)
    - Leitch (Box-folder 2.9)
    - Lobdell (Box-folder 2.10)
    - Lucker, McDougall (Box-folder 2.11)
    - Mahaffey, Mahler (Box-folder 2.12)
    - Meyers (Box-folder 2.13)
    - Millikin, Montville, Morrison (Box-folder 3.1)
    - Power, Reed (Box-folder 3.2)
    - Stevens, Timmons, Walsh, Wehner, Wessling (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Foreign powers of attorney, 1890 - 1920; Includes United Kingdom, Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Paraguay, Peru, Uruguay. (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Fire Dept. permit, 1931; New Brunswick Industries mortgage and bankruptcy, 1932 (Box-folder 3.5)
- Tax records, 1921 - 1936; V; New Brunswick Industries mortgage and bankruptcy, 1932
  - 1921-1936 (Box-folder 3.6)
- Payroll records, 1923 - 1944; VI
  - Utica Mutual payroll audits, January, 1923 - July, 1926 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - Payroll summaries
    - Jan. 1-June 28, 1938 (Box-folder 3.8)
    - June 29, 1938-Jan. 3, 1939 (Box-folder 3.9)
    - Jan. 4-June 27, 1939 (Box-folder 3.10)
    - June 26-Dec. 31, 1940 (Box-folder 3.11)
    - Jan. 1-June 24, 1941 (Box-folder 3.12)
    - June 25-Dec. 31, 1941 (Box-folder 4.1)
    - Jan. 7-June 30, 1942 (4.2)
    - July 1, 1942-Jan. 12, 1943 (Box-folder 4.3)
    - Jan. 13-June 22, 1943 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - June 30, 1943-Jan. 4, 1944 (Box-folder 4.5)
    - Jan. 5-June 27, 1944 (Box-folder 4.6)
- Miscellaneous financial records and correspondence, 1900 - 1944; VII
  - 1900-1926 (Box-folder 7.7)
  - 1928-1936 (Box-folder 7.8)
  - 1938-1940 (Box-folder 7.9)
  - 1941 (Box-folder 7.10)
  - 1942-1944 (Box-folder 7.11)
  - Insurance appraisal and engineering report, 1920/1935 (Box-folder 7.12)
  - Birge Illinois annual reports, 1921 - 1933 (Box-folder 7.13)
- Oversize bound volumes, 1887 - 1944; VIII; Spine labels given in brackets.
  - London office cashbooks, A
    - Dec. 1915-Mar. 1921, 1
    - Apr. 1921-July 1925
    - Aug. 1925-Sept. 1928
    - Sept. 1928-Oct. 1931
  - Trial balance books, B
    - July 1933-June 1936
    - July 1936-June 1939
  - Agents’ sales books, C; Volume date on spine.
    - 1913
    - 1914
    - 1916
    - 1917
    - 1918
    - 1919
  - Ledgers, D
    - 1910-1912 [3]
    - 1914-1918 [4]
    - 1926-1933
  - Journals, E
    - June 1912-May 1913 [4]
    - June 1915-June 1918 [5]
    - June 1921-Sept. 1924
    - Oct. 1924-May 1928 [8]
    - June 1928-July 1932 [9]
    - Aug. 1932-June 1939 [10]
    - July 1939-June 1944
  - Cash expenditure books, F
    - Oct. 1913-Jan. 1915 [10]
    - Feb. 1915-June 1916 [11]
    - July 1916-Feb. 1918 [12]
    - Mar. 1918-Aug. 1919 [13]
    - Sept. 1919-June 1922
    - July 1922-Nov. 1925
    - Dec. 1925-Apr. 1931
    - May 1931-May 1933
  - General cashbooks, G
    - June 1911-June 1914 [4]
    - July 1914-July 1917 [5]
    - July 1917-May 1920 [6]
    - June 1920-Aug. 1922 [7]
    - Sept. 1922-Aug. 1924 [8]
    - Sept. 1924-Aug. 1926 [9]
    - Sept. 1927-Aug. 1928 [10]
    - Sept. 1928-Sept. 1930 [11]
    - Oct. 1930-June 1933 [12]
  - Closed accounts payable, H
    - 1900-1922
  - Salesmen’s accounts book, Arranged alphabetically.; I
  - Inventory books, J
    - Aug. 1900-June 1908
    - July 1908-May 1920
  - Scrapbooks, K
    - 1922-1925, Includes newspaper articles, advertisements, wallpaper history, and press releases.
    - 1932-1935, Includes trade journal advertisements, newspaper articles, and advertisements, wallpaper samples, brochures, and photographs of showrooms, murals, stores selling Birge wallpaper (not local), and national home show.
  - Reproduction d’étoffes orientales tissées en imprimés, L
    - A. Calavas, editeur, 68, rue de Lafayette, Paris, undated.
  - Tag books, M
    - Sample/account book, 1887 - 1888; Includes hand-painted swatches on pages labeled “Block a/c”, “Hangings”, “Borders”, “Extension & corners”, and “Hand”.
    - Tag book #20, 1920; Lists companies next to swatches; includes swatch #5232-7270, and another set of swatch numbers, in no apparent order.
    - Birge colonial papers, Includes swatch #8312-8766.
    - Birge colonial papers, Includes swatch #8766-9106.
    - Authentic colonial wallpapers by Birge, Full-page samples with historic description, price, and pattern number.
    - Hand-made 22-inch hangings
    - The Birge book, ca. 1918-1919; Full-page reproduction leather samples.
    - Book of full-page reproduction leather hangings
    - Book of full-page reproduction leather hangings
    - Book of full-page reproduction leather hangings
    - Book of full-page reproduction leather hangings
  - Pattern illustration books, N
    - The book of illustrations of the new patterns of paper hangings for the season of 1905. Manufactured by M. H. Birge & Sons Co., Buffalo, N.Y., U.S.A., c. 1904. Photographs of rooms with Birge wallcoverings. Stamped on cover: “George K. Birge”.
    - Same as above, ca. 1906. Stamped on cover: “George K. Birge”.
- Photographs and poster, ca. 1900-1955; IX
  - Birge plant with original office complex, 1920 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - Wallpaper designers (2 photos) (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Birge Christmas party, 1946 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - Trade show exhibit (Box-folder 5.4)
  - Sample book illustrations, hand painted (3 photos) (Box-folder 5.5-6)
  - Photographs of paper hangings, from 1904 pamphlet (33 photos) (Box-folder 5.7-5.23)
  - Photographs of paper hangings, unidentified series (3 photos) (Box-folder 5.24)
  - Leather paper used on the galleries of the Royal Scottish Academy, Edinburgh (Box-folder 5.25)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower boyhood home, Abilene, Kansas, with Birge wallpaper restoration (Box-folder 5.26)
  - Photographs of murals (9 photos) (Box-folder 5.27)
  - Scenic wallpaper examples (not Birge), including Portsmouth, New Hampshire Athletic Club (7 photos) (Box-folder 5.28-31)
  - Posters
    - Birge wall papers: the standard of quality, showing the process of machine printing. Works, Buffalo, N.Y., ca. 1930. Ca. 71 x 56 cm.: color.
    - Historical wallcoverings – established in 1834, undated. 51 x 38 cm.
    - Sample of Birge wallpaper, embossed Art Nouveau design in maroon. Exhibited in Esenwein & Johnson exhibit, 2006 (Oversize Drawer C77-2 manuscript room).